<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-08-07T17:58:49-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Your awesome title</title><subtitle>Write an awesome description for your new site here. You can edit this line in _config.yml. It will appear in your document head meta (for Google search results) and in your feed.xml site description.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">My Experience Setting Up My Very Own Server!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/website-server-setup/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My Experience Setting Up My Very Own Server!" /><published>2022-06-08T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-06-08T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/How-To-Set-Up-Five-Websites-On-A-Super-Small-Server</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/website-server-setup/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="rate-my-frogs"><strong>Rate My Frogs</strong></h3>

<p>About a year ago, I had a silly idea about a website whose sole purpose would be
for rating frogs. I used my newfound understanding of web frameworks, and with
the help of a couple of friends, had made my idea into reality! My next step was
going to be to deploy to the web so I could show the website to anyone. Being
the ambitious yet fairly naive student I am, I figured I could cut costs by
purchasing a raspberry pi and set up my very own server to host my websites on
it. And I’m certainly better off for it – even though I temporarily moved away from 
using the raspberry pi, I learned a lot about linux server setup, firewalls,
reverse proxies, and DNS. This brings me to the next part of my server setup
adventure.<br /><br /></p>

<h3 id="donkey-kong-december"><strong>Donkey Kong December</strong></h3>

<p>Silly website ideas are best fueled by impulsive silly domain name purchases 
(which are my favorite kind!). One such example for me was
donkeykongdecember.com, a website intended to tell the user if it is currently
december or not. Needless to say, once I had bought the domain, I knew what I
wanted to create, and tasked myself with creating and deploying it in under an
hour. Luckily for me, my university has freely accessible server space for
students to upload websites/projects. In the hour I used to create and deploy
the website, and I had called the project a success. Of course, the one drawback
is that web deployment on the school server was restricted to users within the
premises of the campus, a problem I soon stumbled upon trying to show it to a
few of my city friends.<br /><br /></p>

<h3 id="rate-my-frogs-version-20"><strong>Rate My Frogs version 2.0</strong></h3>

<p>Flash forward a month in early April, a couple of weeks before my birthday. I
decided to surprise my friends with a new and improved version of
ratemyfrogs.com. By that time in the month, the previous version had been down
for almost 6 months, mostly due to troubles hosting on the raspberry pi. After
completing a new and improved website, the host I chose doesn’t really matter 
(they’re all pretty 
much the same), the important thing is that the past problems I had with each 
new website I made cascaded into the decision to make that purchase.<br /><br /></p>

<h3 id="carpool-bot"><strong>Carpool Bot</strong></h3>

<p>I took a small break from websites to develop a discord bot with a new discord
python library I found. Admittedly it’s still a bit buggy at the time of writing
this, but it’s something I hope to take another look at in the future. <br /><br /></p>

<h3 id="gitea"><strong>Gitea</strong></h3>

<p>My latest development, learning how git remote servers work! This stemmed mostly
from curiosity on self-hosted git, and started off as a project to try to make
my own git server front-end! Admittedly I ended up using gitea, an existing
solution, over anything I built, but in the end that allowed me to spend more time
understanding how remote git servers work. I hope to port the site to https
sometime soon, and use it as a portfolio of carefully curated projects for
visitors to my website to see!<br /><br /></p>

<h3 id="emilkovacevcom"><strong>emilkovacev.com</strong></h3>

<p>Yes, my personal website is next! With my server, I am going to add a few more
features to my website to make it more interactive (I’m thinking of an email
notification form?) It was initially written in Jekyll so I could host on GitHub
Pages for free, but now I use it because I made a custom theme for it 
(emilkovacev/aeroplane)!<br /><br /></p>

<h3 id="but-why"><strong>But Why?</strong></h3>

<p>“Enough with the storytelling already” you must be thinking. And I suppose
you’re right, the story isn’t quite as compelling as the act of doing it
yourself. But I hope those excertps showed you even just a small bit of 
insight into how I ended up learning these concepts, and why they’re important
to me. Having fun with websites was a better motivator for me than any strict
regimen or habitual motivation could ever be.<br /><br /></p>

<h3 id="prerequisites"><strong>Prerequisites</strong></h3>

<p>I am assuming that readers of this post are familiar with the linux command
line, to the point of understanding general shell commands.<br /><br /></p>

<h3 id="the-how"><strong>The How</strong></h3>

<p>Here’s the step-by-step tutorial you may be looking for. Instead of focusing 
on the general case, here’s how I deployed ratemyfrogs.com!</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>I used DigitalOcean for my newest server, but was previously (at the time of
writing this article) a Linode user. Both services are fairly simple to setup, 
but I think DigitalOcean can be more affordable.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>For digitalocean, you need to create a droplet to host your project on. A 
“droplet” is DigitalOcean’s fancy name for a server. I recommend using Ubuntu
20.04 if you haven’t tinkered around with using other distros before. (Note,
RateMyFrogs.com uses MongoDB, which currently does not support Ubuntu 22.04
yet. DigitalOcean defaults to v22.04 when you select it, so be sure to change
it if you want it to run properly).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>SSH into your vm. SSH is essentially your method of entering the vm remotely. 
Any time you want to remotely access a droplet (server) by its ip address, you can use the
ssh command. In this case, since we are using ubuntu, the base
user is <em>root</em>, and our ip address (alternatively listed as ipv4) should be 
listed with the droplet. 
Run the ssh command</p>

    <p><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">$ ssh root@&amp;lt;ip&amp;gt;</code></p>

    <p>to access the your vm with ip address <ip>, as 
the root user. Enter your the password from earlier when prompted. 
You may be prompted to confirm your connection if "the
authenticity of the host can't be established", in which case you type `yes`
and continue. By now, you should recieve a prompt that confirms that you have
successfully accessed the linode server.</ip></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Now it’s time to setup a user for yourself, so you don’t use root all the 
time. Why shouldn’t you continue to use root? Root access is pretty powerful,
meaning you would have pretty unlimited access to important files and the
ability to delete files you may not want to delete. Use the command <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">sudo
adduser &lt;username&gt;</code>, where <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">&lt;username&gt;</code> is the username you choose for your
user. The command line will then prompt you for a few details regarding your
new user, fill them in appropriately, and if you want to skip a question
click <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Enter</code>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Now it’s time to install all prerequisite software! First, we need to install
MongoDB. I used <a href="https://www.mongodb.com/docs/manual/tutorial/install-mongodb-on-ubuntu/">this</a>
tutorial to install it:</p>

    <ol>
      <li>
        <p>Import the public key used by the package management system:<br />
<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">$ wget -qO - https://www.mongodb.org/static/pgp/server-6.0.asc | sudo apt-key add -</code></p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>Create a list file for MongoDB:<br />
<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">$ echo "deb [ arch=amd64,arm64 ] https://repo.mongodb.org/apt/ubuntu focal/mongodb-org/6.0 multiverse" | sudo tee /etc/apt/sources.list.d/mongodb-org-6.0.list</code></p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>Reload local package database:<br />
<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">$ sudo apt-get update</code></p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>Install the MongoDB packages:<br />
<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">$ sudo apt-get install -y mongodb-org</code></p>
      </li>
    </ol>

    <p>Now we want to install nginx:</p>

    <ol>
      <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">$ sudo apt update</code></li>
      <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">$ sudo apt install nginx</code></li>
    </ol>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Clone the <a href="https://github.com/emilkovacev/ratemyfrogs">repo for ratemyfrogs.com</a>.
Switch to the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">rework</code> branch. The following instructions are also in the
README.md file.</p>

    <ol>
      <li>
        <p>setup a venv<br />
<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">$ python -m venv venv</code></p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>install requirements<br />
<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">$ python3 -m pip install -r requirements.txt</code></p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p><em>We already set up MongoDB from earlier, so we can skip this step!</em></p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>Run the server 
<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">uvicorn server:app --port=5001</code></p>
      </li>
    </ol>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Change the DNS in your domain provider to reflect the correct ip address. I
prefer cloudflare for the free ssl proxies, but any alternative works.
Generally speaking, this is usually an A record with the host being @
(home) and the “points to” is the public-facing server ip.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p><strong>If you completed steps 1-9, you should have a fully-functioning live
deployed website!</strong></p>

<p>– Emil Lars Kovačev<br /><br /></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Tech Stuff" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Rate My Frogs]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Little History of the World by E.H. Gombrich</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/a-little-history-of-the-world/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Little History of the World by E.H. Gombrich" /><published>2022-01-23T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-01-23T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/A-Little-History-of-the-World</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/a-little-history-of-the-world/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="introduction">Introduction</h3>

<p>In recent months, I began to realize that my understanding of history was very
muddled. I couldn’t tell you the dates, order, or any significant contributions
of ancient civilizations. Nor could I recount important periods, people, general
developments, etc. While I could point many fingers to many people, including
myself (I acknowledge I played a large part in my ignorance), I find this first
and foremost to be a failure of American education. Middle school and high
school rarely ever focused on developing the foundation for history necessary to
properly analyze contemporary historical events. Teachers focused on building
analytical skills for passages and piecing together certain points of view - all
important skills for a historian, but less meaningful without proper context. I
have plenty of additional thoughts on the subject of education, but I will have
to save them for another time. Needless to say, I was unsatisfied with my
understanding of human history, and sought a book to relearn many of those
essential concepts. I am delighted to announce that <em>A Little History of the
World</em> was the perfect companion to get me back on track.<br /><br /></p>

<h3 id="a-childrens-book-not-a-book-for-children">A Children’s Book, Not A Book for Children</h3>

<p>Growing up, I was never especially enthralled by history classes. Most of them
focused on precise, direct causes and effects that led to revolutions and
changes in lifestyle. During the Renaissance for instance, it is easy to
describe the impact that ancient Greece had on the architecture, art, and law in
Italy. But (I would argue) it is <em>more</em> important to understand that the
Renaissance occurred contrary to the lifestyle of the Middle Ages, following a
long period of Feudalism. Somewhat ironically, Italy’s recapture of antiquity
marked the beginning of the New Age. Understanding the background, the <em>what
came before</em> is something that <em>A Little History of the World</em> introduces and
expands on wonderfully.</p>

<p>When assigned to write this novel, as mentioned in the introduction, Gombrich
was well aware of his audience and his constraints. He started the book by
making a solemn promise (only broken a handful of times and for very explicit
reasons) to provide a who, what, and when within his descriptions of historical
events. As an addition, Gombrich approached <em>A Little History of the World</em> with
little formality, and introduced complexity through <em>ideas</em>, generally by
examining the effects that dozens of previous chapters in history had on the
chapter he was narrating. It was written as a children’s book by design -
however <em>A Little History of the World</em> is still valuable to readers of all ages
looking to standardize history, and put it into context. If you were to read its
reviews on the back of the cover, you would find a general consensus in this:
book critics love this book, and for good reason. As of right now, it is without
a doubt my favorite book.<br /><br /></p>

<h3 id="reading-history">Reading History</h3>

<p>As I mentioned earlier, I was not dedicated to reinforce my understanding of
historical events prior to reading <em>A Little History of the World</em>. Fortunately,
and rather excitingly, Gombrich’s exploration in human historical events,
recounting epic tales from the dawn of civilization to brilliant and ruthless
emperors and leaders, to conquests on behalf of faith and knowledge, has kindled
a curiosity within me. This book serves mostly as an atlas, a guide through the
ages of civilization if you will. I fully intend to explore some of my favorite
sections in more detail, including ancient Greek and Chinese civilization, the
conquests of Alexander the Great, Confucian philosophy, the Renaissance, and
most surprisingly of all, Napoleon’s reign in post—revolutionary France! If you, the
reader, are in desperate need to rekindle your passion for history, or are
perhaps looking to strengthen and contextualize human civilization from
antiquity to WWII, <em>A Little History of the World</em> is the perfect book to start
with.<br /><br /></p>

<p><em>- Emil Lars Kovačev</em><br /><br /></p>

<h3 id="corrections">Corrections</h3>

<h4 id="2022-01-23">2022-01-23</h4>
<ul>
  <li>Revised wording of renaissance influences</li>
  <li>Corrected title of ancient Greece</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Book Review" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Introduction]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/a-little-history-of-the-world.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/a-little-history-of-the-world.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Discrete Charm of the Machine by Ken Steiglitz</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/the-discrete-charm-of-the-machine/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Discrete Charm of the Machine by Ken Steiglitz" /><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-01-05T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/The-Discrete-Charm-of-the-Machine</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/the-discrete-charm-of-the-machine/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="introduction">Introduction</h3>

<p>In the early 19<sup>th</sup> century, foundational discoveries in the field of 
mathematics, physics, chemistry, and, oddly enough, embroidery paved 
the way to developing the lightning-quick computers we rely on today. 
Steiglitz explores the course of impact of these discoveries to inform 
the reader on how he believes technology will advance in the future.<br /><br /></p>

<h3 id="more-history-than-science">More History Than Science</h3>

<p>Steiglitz’s most exciting literary choice, as prefaced by his quip 
in the introduction, was to leave (most) equations out. The book is 
written for a general audience; Steiglitz includes clear explanations of 
scientific and mathematical material he reviews, although some 
material benefitted from background knowledge. Steiglitz has successfully 
written an approachable, in-depth narrative on analog and digital machines.
However, <em>The Discrete Charm of the Machine</em> still has much to offer to 
seasoned computer science veterans. Especially in the treasure trove of the 
footnotes, where he hides small tidbits, proofs, papers, and the 
occasional mention of the <em>Antikythera device</em> that veers off his train 
of thought. The resources he includes are a nice addition for those looking 
for more specialized readings on the book’s topics but are not essential to 
illustrate the big picture.</p>

<div class="image">
    <img src="/assets/images/antikythera_model.jpeg" />
    <figcaption><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antikythera_mechanism">
        A modern replica of the Ancient Greek Antikythera mechanism</a>, 
        a device Steiglitz frequently cites in his descriptions of analog machinery
    </figcaption>
</div>

<p>Narrative structure plays a significant role in how Steiglitz portrays 
his timeline. At the heart of <em>The Discrete Charm of the Machine</em> is 
Steiglitz’s definition of a modern computer, which is broken up into 
six general concepts revealed by the discoveries he writes about. 
Each chapter draws the reader closer to his definition until we get 
a clear understanding of the path history took to reach our level 
of machine sophistication. The book rarely abides to chronology and 
to great effect. Instead, Steiglitz chooses to highlight the advantages 
that digital machines had over analog ones, a concept which he discusses 
in great detail. He does this by alternating descriptions of analog
machines and their digital counterparts, focusing on what each machine
contributed towards his definition of a modern computer. Despite this, 
the reader is never left behind, unless they are willing to follow 
the footnotes in great detail. The brilliance of <em>The Discrete Charm 
of the Machine</em> is in its simplicity.<br /><br /></p>

<h3 id="final-thoughts">Final Thoughts</h3>

<p>Steiglitz excels in providing context to the quick advancement of digital 
machines. He expertly describes fundamental computing topics like ‘transistors’ 
and ‘NP-complete algorithms’, tying them together to form a basic understanding 
of new emerging fields in computer science. <em>The Discrete Charm of the Machine</em> 
is a must-read for computer science enthusiasts and casual readers
alike.<br /><br /></p>

<p>– Emil Lars Kovačev<br /><br /></p>

<h3 id="corrections">Corrections</h3>
<h4 id="2022-01-23">2022-01-23</h4>

<ul>
  <li>Added categories (Introduction, More History Than Science, Final Thoughts)</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Book Review" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Introduction]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/the-discrete-charm-of-the-machine.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/the-discrete-charm-of-the-machine.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>